<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
        <rss version='2.0'>
            <channel>
                <title>GeolHistory Articles</title>
                <link>https://geolhistory.org/articles</link>
                <description>GeolHistory Articles</description>
                <language>en-us</language>
                <image>
                    <url>https://geolhistory.org/storage/images/social-image.jpg</url>
                    <title>GeolHistory Articles</title>
                    <link>https://geolhistory.org/articles</link>
                </image>
                <item>
                    <title>Welcome</title>
                    <link>https://geolhistory.org/articles/1</link>
                    <description>Welcome to our Articles Section of GeolHistory. Here you'll find articles written by our amazing writing team about geological news, events and just about anything else that doesn't fit into one of our existing pages. These articles are written, referenced and checked entirely by the writer whose name is displayed in the article's header, so make sure to credit them if you use their work. We and our writers love to hear what you think about our content. If you'd like to contact a member of our writing team please email contact@geolhistory.org with your message and the article that you're contacting us about, and we'll pass your message on to the writer. Our writing team is currently invite-only. However, if you currently study Geology at Runshaw College or the University of Plymouth, you can email contact@geolhistory.org for an invite code. Sorry! Sometimes we make mistakes, please email contact@geolhistory.org and let us know what you think is wrong. Thank you.</description>
                    <author>lewis.milburn@lmwn.co.uk (Ben Mackley)</author>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <title>Metamorphic Rocks</title>
                    <link>https://geolhistory.org/articles/2</link>
                    <description>Metamorphism - what exactly is it?Metamorphism is the term used to describe the recrystallisation of minerals in rocks. This always occurs at solid-state and the changes are isocheimal, meaning that no elements are added or removed (apart from volatiles e.g. carbon dioxide and water). There are three types of metamorphism: Regional metamorphism, which requires both heat and pressure.Contact metamorphism, which requires JUST heat.Dynamic metamorphism, which occurs at fault zones, where friction between the rocks create heat. What may occur during metamorphism?Metamorphism of a rock may result in a series of changes in the rock's properties, possible changes include: Texture and alignment of minerals (foliation)Hardening of rockNew metamorphic minerals may be formedDestruction of fossils, beds and sedimentary structures.Note: A parent rock is called a protolith (example: the protolith of marble is limestone) Equilibrium dynamicsThis states that all reactions are reversible. Contact MetamorphismThis only involves heat, meaning that pressures are low and minerals aren't foliated. Contact metamorphism occurs next to igneous intrusions. An example of contact metamorphism is the aureole formed around a batholith or pluton. An important thing to remember is that the size of the contact metamorphism depends on a multitude of factors:Volume of the intrusionType of country rockDifference in temperaturesType of magmaTemperature of the intrusion. Dynamic MetamorphismThis occurs at fault zones, where heat is generated from friction, from the cataclasis of the rocks.Cataclasis is the term for the mechanical action of grinding and crushing the rocks. This produces angular fragments (for example fault breccia).Recrystallisation may occur when the temperature and directed stress is very high, which produces smaller, stable and unstrained crystals (known as mylonite) Regional MetamorphismThis involves both heat and directed stress, and occurs at plate boundaries, over large areas. Commonly show rock deformation. All regional metamorphic rocks with platy minerals have a foliation. This is where the minerals in the rock recrystallize and the flat, platy minerals (e.g. clay) align themselves perpendicular to the direction of stress. Regional metamorphic rocks formed from shale.Parent rockMetamorphic rockColourTextureMineralsType of MetamorphismShale SlateBlack, grey, green or purpleFine-grained (</description>
                    <author>lewis.milburn@lmwn.co.uk (Alice Forshaw)</author>
                </item>
            </channel>
        </rss>